
Source: Competitive and Market Analysis for Product Managers

01.Market research - Sizing the market

Top down & Bottom up

Top down: Based on total market size, optimistic
Finding the total market and estimate what your market share is

Bottom up: Based on current trends, conservative
Current sales of similar product

Ways:
Industry reports of __
Google keyword planner
Compete: search for website traffic

02.Introduction to finding competitors

Feature Triage:
1. Get your more users
2. Make your users happy
3. Enhance your brand

Look at your competitors:
What they look like
What they are doing
What they offer

03.Find competitors as a product manager
Step 1: capture
Your company versus __
Focus on problems: what problem does this solve?

Techniques:
#1. Channel the type of user
How do they complain about the problem?

You'll find:
1. Companies that are using that verbiage
2. Individual complaints online
3. Google connects the dots

reddit.com
Quora.com
Yahoo answers

#2: Describe what your product does
You'll find:
1. Companies using literal descriptions
2. Ads at the top of the search list
3. Google's input

#3: play around with quotation marks: ""
#4: figure how you'll pitch it

04.Direct, indirect, and potential competitors and their impact

4 different types of competitors:
Direct
Indirect
Potential 
Substitue

Eg., pasta restaurant
Direct: similar product, same target market, Italian food restaurant
Indirect: same problem, different type of product, greek food restaurant => not losing too many customers
Potential: different problem, potential competitor in the future, Italian grocery stores => make sure they can't do it easily
Substitue: same problem, different way, big size and market power, pizza hut => be at lease better than these

05.The five criteria for understanding competitors

#1: the product core
How good is our competitors's product team?
Know how good their product core is
#2: user base: know the size of their user base

06.The last three criteria for understanding competitors
#3 design
#4 brand
#5 speed


07.Monitor competitors
[Criteria for judging your competitors]
1. Product team
2. Design
3. Brand
4. User base
5. Speed

#1 funding
CrunchBase
#2 acquisitions
#3 new features/products
mention.com: follow your competitors
Google alert

08.What is a feature table

x:#1 #2 #3 competitors YOU
Y: dimensions

How competitive you are?


09.Put together a feature table
Why should they choose you?
What is important to your customer group?

x:#1 #2 #3 competitors YOU
Y: dimensions (price, reliability, feature X, ability to do Y, aesthetics, weight ...)

10.Practice building a feature table

x:#1 #2 #3 competitors YOU
Y: dimensions (price, reliability, feature X, ability to do Y, aesthetics, weight ...)

11.What do you ultimately care about as a product manager

[competitors]
See what they have in common
How users are interacting with them
What I can learn from the lessons they've learned
