Source: B2B Marketing Foundations - Positioning

1.Introduction
03.What customers buy and what they don't

Customer buy:
Benefits
Quality
Convenience

B2B customers buy value
Value based messaging

Successful Messaging:
Clear understanding of buyer
Problem to be solved
Understanding of alternative solutions

2.1. Value Messaging Overview
04.The key elements of B2B positioning
Who, what, why

Elements of a Positioning Statement
1. Target customer
2. Problem to be solved
3. Product category
4. Unique value
5. Differentiated capabilities that deliver value

For [target customers] who need to [solve this problem][your product] is a [category].
Unlike competitors such as ABC and XYZ, [your product] delivers [these 3-5 unique value statements] by providing [differentiated capabilities].

Target Market: Critical to define to be meaningful and valuable
Problem to Solve: Big enough to get attention but not overreaching
Category: Stating you're part of an existing or new category
Unique Value: Business benefits the customer exchanges time and money for

Customer buy [values], not [features]

05.Targeting - Why, what, and how

Defining and understanding your target market is critical to success

Defined Target Market:
Narrows your focus
Describes goods and services in a concrete, actionable way

Target Market Specifics:
Titles and responsibilities (of buyers)
Firmographics (industry, size of company, markets they serve, their go-to-market strategies)
Geography

06.Identifying the big problem

What problem did you solve?
Problem Statement:
Who do you solve problem for?
What problem do you solve?

07.Category
Product Categories:
1. We fit in an existing category
2. We fit, but we're different
3. We fit, and we do something else
4. We're something new

08.Differentiation and unique value

Axiology:
The study of value

Mastering Value:
What is value and who defines it?
What is value discovery?
What is unique value?

Defining Value:
The specific benefit a customer exchanges their time and money for

Discovering Value:
Features and capabilities => Customer benefits => Value

3.2. Building Candidate Value Statement - Benefits
09.Three steps to unique value

Steps to Unique Value:
1. Inventory
2. Translate
3. Filter

1. Inventory
Features are tangible and specific
Capabilities are higher level

2. Translate
Benefits the features can deliver

3. Filter
Does the customer care?
Does the competitor deliver this value? 
Find 3-5 unique value statements

10.Key feature and capability inventory
Features and Capabilities:
The engines that deliver by themselves, or in combination with each other, business benefits to the customer

Focus on the features that matter

List the features and benefits that are meaningful in delivering value

Building an Inventory:
Find existing resources
Start big
More, not less (add all the features you can think of)
Be inclusive, not exhaustive
Don't list benefits yet
Use a spreadsheet

11.The five types of B2B business benefits
[Business Benefits]
Cost savings (tangible/measurable)
Revenue increases
Risk reduction
Business agility increases
Innovation enablement or improvement
(Intangible/hard to measure)

12.Getting beyond generic benefits

Generic=>Specific
How much
How many
How quickly
For who
For what
Why

Saves Time and Money
1. Saves time in the manufacturing process (generic)
2. Saves 5% of assembly time for all automated fastening operations
3. Saves 5% of assembly time for all automated fattening operations, by eliminating 90% or more of rework
4. Saves 5% of assembly time for all automated plastic fastening operations, by eliminating 90% or more of rework
(More specific)

Increases Revenue
Adds 3% price premium to products
Adds 3% price premium to product lines by improving promotional effectiveness at retail

Risk Reduction
Decreases malware exposure on mobile phones
Decreases mobile secrurity risk

Find the benefits that drive customer decisions

13.Creating a benefits statement

What specific business benefit does this feature deliver?
[Building benefits statements]
1. Approach from a customer perspective
2. Logical mapping
3. Generic to spefitic

14.Crafting your messaging

Assemble a Team:
Sales
Customer service
Implementation
Product management

Explain Business Benefits:
Review generic types
Show examples

15.Why benefits are just the start

Challenges:
Value is in the eye of the beholder
Value is relative
Value is subjective

[The benefits delivered that matter enough to buyers to motivate purchase]
-
[Those available from alternative solutions]
=
Unique Value

16.Supporting your key messages
<Messaging Chapters>
Features and capabilities
Customer pain points
Proof points

17.Building your positioning statement
<Elements of a positioning statement>
1. Target customer
2. Problem to be solved
3. Product category
4. Unique value
5. Differentiated capabilities that deliver value

For [target customers] who need to [solve this problem][your product] is a [category].
Unlike competitors such as ABC and XYZ, [your product] delivers [these 3-5 unique value statements] by providing [differentiated capabilities].

1. [target merket]
Critical to define to be meaningful and valuable
2. [problem to solve]
Big enough to get attention but not overreaching
3. [category]
Stating you're part of an existing or new category
4. [unique value]
Business benefits the customer exchanges time and money for

18.Implementing your message

[Implementation]
1. Define the work at hand
2. Take inventory
3. Execute

19.Why it matters

Know your audience, and connect with what they value
[Business benefits]
Cost savings
Revenue increases
Risk reduction
Business agility increases
Innovation enablement or improvement

[Steps to Unique Value]
1. Inventory
2. Translate
3. Filter

20.Beyond value to your magical story
Marketers tend to overvalue value

[Marketing Storytelling]
Hero: customer
Battleground: problem solved
Magic: out product
Bestow: unique value

1. Problem to solve
2. Features inventory
3. Unique value

21.Summary story




